Guide to the Time Inc. Time-Life News Service Records 1935-1987 MS 3009-RG 14
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Time-Life News Service Records
1935-1987
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 14
115.8 Linear feet in 114 record cartons, 1 flat box
The Time-Life News Service Records documents the management and activities of Time Inc.'s news gathering branch. While the department was formally part of Time magazine for most of its history, it gathered and reported on news for other magazines as well. The collection contains records from the chiefs of correspondents and their office, records from the New York Regional Bureau Chief, financial records, personnel and biographical files assembled on employees of the Time-Life News Service, dispatches and article research material that did not end up in the Time Research Center, and correspondence discussing masthead changes concerning Time-Life News Service staff. Due to overlap of financial management between the Time magazine business office and Time-Life New Service's financial office, financial records include Time budgets as well as financial documents for Time Inc. subsidiaries such as the Washington Star.
Historical Note
According to documents found in the News Service History file within the General File of the Chief of Correspondents Series, Time hired David Hulburd in Fall 1929 to report news from Chicago. Stationed in a room next to the advertising office, Hulburd was tasked with monitoring the Midwest for news that was worth national attention. Every day, Hulburd would send back bundles of clippings to Time's editorial offices in New York, and, if a reporter found a story they were interested in, the reporter would contact the Research Department to follow up with that newspaper or news service for additional details. The Research Department was headed by Mary Fraiser. News agencies contacted included the United Press Association or the Associated Press. If the Research Department received a reply, Fraser would pay the source. To help Time gain more sources of news, Hulburd began traveling the country in 1935 to set up other news offices to gather regional stories. The first office was in San Francisco and the next was in Los Angeles.
Fraser recognized that relying on other news organizations for details and reports was unreliable, and Time did not always receive replies to its queries. Fraser and Hulburd began setting up Time's own domestic and international news bureaus in 1937. In a staff memorandum sent out before his retirement, Hulburd noted that Fraser's encouragement and influence was one of the biggest factors in his decision, as well as the decision of other reporters, to work for Time and put in the effort to build the bureau of correspondents.
Hulburd was in charge of managing the bureaus and offices throughout the United States, Europe, and Asia. For the first few years, the bureaus remained under the Research Department. With the creation of their own news service, Time began to hire correspondents and stringers and relied less upon the United Press Association. Time Inc. still contracted with the Associated Press for their other publications. In 1941, the news service was placed under the authority of Henry Luce as Time's editor. Around this same time, correspondents for other Time Inc. publications began maintaining news desks in the Time news bureau offices beginning with Rachel Albertson from Life.
From 1937 through most of 1945, Hulburd oversaw both the domestic and foreign correspondents. At this point, the size of the bureaus and number of people employed became too cumbersome for one person, and domestic and foreign affairs were separated. The domestic news service remained part of Time, but was overseen by the senior editors. During the time that the domestic news service was part of Time, the department under went a number of name changes. In 1951 it was the Newsbureau, but became the U.S. and Canadian New Service.
The foreign service was moved to Time-Life International, also known as TLI, and was known as the TLI Foreign Desk. The foreign service remained under TLI until around 1954. At this point, the foreign service appears to have been removed from TLI's jurisdiction and became its own department known as the Overseas Bureaus. By 1960, the department's name was changed to the Foreign News Service. During this period, domestic news bureau chiefs were listed as assistant editors at Time in the department heads lists, but foreign news bureau chiefs were not. Materials within the collection imply that foreign news bureau chiefs were staff at Time but they did not seem to receive the same status domestic bureau chiefs.
The foreign and domestic bureaus continued to operate separately until 1962 when they were once again placed under one news chief who also held a position at Time as an assistant editor. Richard Clurman, who had been chief of domestic correspondents, became chief of both foreign and domestic correspondents. At first, the new united system was known as the Time News Service but this name was quickly changed to the Time-Life News Service. Despite only have the names of Time and Life in the title, the chief of bureaus appeared to oversee correspondents and stringers for all of Time Inc.'s magazines. One such organization was the Washington Star which was owned by Time Inc. between 1978 and 1981. During the time that Time Inc. owned the Washington Star, the newspaper operated as a separate organization but did not have any of their own correspondents or stringers. Rather than hiring their own set of correspondents and stringers, the Time-Life News Service provided personnel to work for the Washington Star, and the Washington Star paid the Time-Life News Service for their service. While suppling news for magazines throughout Time Inc., the Time-Life News Service remained part of Time's editorial operations until 1985 when the news service became part of the Magazine Group.
Scope and Contents
The Time-Life News Service Records documents the management and activities of Time Inc.'s news gathering branch.
The collection contains records from the chiefs of correspondents and their office, records from the New York Regional Bureau Chief, financial records, personnel and biographical files assembled on employees of the Time-Life News Service, dispatches and article research material that did not end up in the Time Research Center, and correspondence discussing masthead changes concerning Time-Life News Service staff. Due to overlap of financial management between the Time magazine business office and Time-Life New Service's financial office, financial records include Time budgets as well as financial documents for Time Inc. subsidiaries such as the Washington Star.
The staff represented in these documents include Dick Duncan, Murray Gart, Richard Clurman, John Boyle, Emmet Hughes, Manfred Gottfried, Ben Cate, Suzanne Davis, Linda Vartoogian, and Camille Cassata. Records include correspondence, dispatches, staff files, notes, interview and speech transcripts, photographs, news clippings, budgets, expense reports, policies, and employee lists.
Microfilm of extensive correspondent cables containing raw reporting and dispatches are located in Series IV of the Time Inc. Time Research Center Files (MS 3009-RG 13).
Arrangement
This record group is arranged into six series:
Series I. Chief of Correspondent Files
Series II. New York Regional Bureau Chief and Senior Correspondent Laurence I. Barrett Files
Series III. Financial Files
Series IV. Staff Files
Series V. Dispatches and Article Research Files
Series VI. Masthead Files
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include contracts, medical reports, correspondence with personally identifying information, staff files from 1975 and forward, reviews and recommendations for personnel, job applications with personally identifying information, expense reports with personally identifying information, and forms with direct deposit information. Restricted boxes include R44 through R55. Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Additional records on the history of the Time-Life News Service are in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1).
Microfilm of extensive correspondent cables containing raw reporting and dispatches are located in Series IV of the Time Inc. Time Research Center Files (MS 3009-RG 13).
Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporation records.; Correspondence.; Dispatches; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Financial records.; Foreign correspondents; Interviews.; Journalists -- United States.; Notes (documents); Organization files.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reporters and reporting -- United States.; Barrett, Laurence I.; Boyle, John W., 1910?-1974; Clurman, Richard M.; Donovan, Hedley; Duncan, Richard; Gart, Murray; Gottfried, Manfred, 1900-1985; Hughes, Emmet John, 1920-; Hulburd, David W.; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History
- Series I. Chief of Correspondent Files, 1935-1987; 60.5 Linear feet in 60 record cartons, 1 flat box
  Scope and Contents
  The Chief of Correspondents files contain materials collected by the Time-Life News Service chiefs of correspondents through 1987. The majority of files were created between 1941 and 1987. Included in this series are payroll forms, employment applications, resumes and CVs, clippings, invitations, guests lists, dispatches, translated articles, benefits summary sheets, annual reports, awards ceremony pamphlets, requisition forms, biographical summaries, press releases, conflict of interest and employment policies, department heads lists, error reports, evaluation guidelines, meeting transcripts, photos, negatives, contact lists, prospectuses, lists of Time Inc. board members, news bureau surveys and results, distribution lists, financial statements and reports, seating lists and charts for meetings and luncheons, vacation schedules, query sheets, lists of bureau staff, immigration and visa forms, reports on newstour participants, background research reports for newstours, reports on the public's attitudes toward Time, and memorandums and correspondence.
  Arrangement
  Arranged into five subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Chief of Correspondents Emmet Hughes Files
  Subseries I.B. Chief of Correspondents Murray Gart Files
  Subseries I.C. Chief of Correspondent Richard Duncan Files
  Subseries I.D. General Files
  Subseries I.E. Bureau Files
  - Subseries I.A. Overseas Bureau and Foreign News Chief Emmet Hughes Files, 1943-1944, 1957-1960; .75 Linear feet in 1 record carton
    Biographical Note
    After graduating from Princeton University in 1941, Emmet John Hughes began to work as a press attache in the United States Embassy at Madrid. From there, Hughes was transferred to Office of War Information in Spain where he directed propaganda. Once the war had ended, Hughes joined Time Inc. During his intermittent employment with Time Inc., Hughes served as bureau chief, foreign news chief, and editor. Besides his work at Time Inc., Hughes served as on President Eisenhower's campaign as a speech writer, worked as a political adviser and speechwriter for Governor Rockefeller in New York, and as a professor at Rutgers University. While at Rutgers, Hughes published a number of books on foreign policy and politics.
    Citations:
    "Emmet Hughes, 61, Journalist; Speechwriter for Eisenhower" New York Times. September 20, 1982. Accessed May 28, 2019. https://www.nytimes.com/1982/09/20/obituaries/emmet-hughes-61-journalist-speechwriter-for-eisenhower.html
    The Emmet Hughes Files contain correspondence, memorandum, and dispatches that Hughes received while acting as Foreign News Chief. While these materials were found with other chief of correspondent files, these materials were separated since they had a different organization, different folders, and a single collector. The correspondence and memorandum included in this subseries provide reactions and summaries to articles as well as bureau updates.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Bureaus: Beirut, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 7)
    - Bureaus: Bonn, 1957 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 8)
    - Bureaus: Buenos Aires, 1957 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 9)
    - Bureaus: The Hague, 1958 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 10)
    - Bureaus: Hong Kong, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 11)
    - Bureaus: Johannesburg, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 12)
    - Bureaus: London, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 13-14)
    - Bureaus: London: Invasion Set Up, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 15)
    - Bureaus: Mexico City, 1957 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 16)
    - Bureaus: New Delhi, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 17)
    - Bureaus: Other, 1958, undated (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 18)
    - Bureaus: Paris, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 19)
    - Bureaus: Rome, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 20)
    - Bureaus: Tokyo, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 21)
    - Memoranda: Foreign News, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 22-28)
    - Memoranda: Foreign News: Personnel Changes, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 29-42)
  - Subseries I.B. Chief of Correspondents Murray Gart Files, 1971-1976; 1.8 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
    After working as editor at Weekly Independent Record in Cape May County, N.J., and as editor and farm reporter for newspapers in Wichita in the early 1950s, Murray Gart began his career with Time Inc. as a stringer for the Time-Life News Service but was soon hired as a correspondent. By the early 1960s he was promoted to bureau chief. Between 1969 and 1977, Gart served as the Time-Life News Service's chief of correspondents but left this position in 1978 to become the editor of the Washington Star. Due to financial issues, the Washington Star folded in 1981. At this time, Gart returned to Time-Life News Service, a subsidiary of Time Inc.,as a senior correspondent and later served as a consultant.
    "Murray Gart, Last Editor of Washington Star, Dies". The Washington Post. Accessed May 28, 2019. https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/local/2004/04/03/murray-gart-last-editor-of-washington-star-dies/a308ffa4-275c-4039-be85-8146167321d6/?utm_term=.63f5b435caf1
    Personnel and Organization: Department Head Lists. Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
    The Murray Gart Files contain materials collected by or sent to Gart from 1971 to 1976. Originally found with corporate editorial records, these files were separated and placed with the chief of correspondents' materials when it was discovered that Gart was the creator of these records. The type of materials in this subseries are similar to the materials found the General Files subseries within the Chief of Correspondent Files. Contained in this subseries are budgets, marketing reports, popularity reports, industry reports, executive summaries, lists of staff, dispatches, salary reports, affirmative action reports, meeting attendee lists, conflict of interest policy drafts, meeting agenda, and correspondence. Correspondence in this subseries discusses hiring, circulation, contract negotiations, New York City municipal work strikes, travel schedules, discrimination, traineeship programs, budgets and expenses, conflicts of interests, cost control, staffing changes, and lawsuits.
    - Affirmative Action Program, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 43)
    - Books and Arts Associations: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 44)
    - Books Division, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3184, Folder 45)
    - Books Division, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 1)
    - Conflict of Interest, 1971-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 2-3)
    - Contributions Committee, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 4)
    - Corporate Management Committee, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 5)
    - Corporate Manufacturing and Distribution: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 6)
    - Cost Control, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 7)
    - Editorial Services, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 8)
    - Firestone Libel Case, 1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 9)
    - Forest Products: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 10)
    - Fortune, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 11)
    - Fortune: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 12)
    - FYI Candidates, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 13)
    - Headcount, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 14)
    - Hiring Freeze, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 15-16)
    - Home Box Office (HBO), 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 17)
    - Home Box Office (HBO): Budget and Two Year Plan, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 18)
    - Laybourne, Larry, 1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 19)
    - Legal Department, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 20)
    - Life: Special Report: Politics, 1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 21)
    - Little, Brown, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 22)
    - Magazine Development: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 23)
    - Magazine Study, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 24)
    - Managing Editors Lunches, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 25-26)
    - Manhattan Cable TV: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 27)
    - Mili, Gjon, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 28)
    - Money: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 29)
    - People, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 30)
    - People: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 31)
    - Personnel, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 32-33)
    - Personnel Issues, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 34)
    - Picture Collection, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 35)
    - Pioneer Press: Budget: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 36)
    - Planning: the three-year, 1973 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 37)
    - Policies, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 38)
    - Postal, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 39-40)
    - Press: Freedom of Subpoena, 1973 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 41)
    - Reader's Digest [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R45)
    - Real Estate: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976 (Offsite-box 3185, Folder 42)
    - Reprint Permission, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 1)
    - Salary Data, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 2)
    - SAMI: Budget and Two Year Plan, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 3)
    - Shepley, James, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 4)
    - South American Trip: Heiskell and Donovan, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 5)
    - Sports Illustrated, undated (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 6)
    - Sports Illustrated: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 7)
    - Strike, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 8)
    - Subpoenas, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 9)
    - Subscription Services: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 10)
    - Temple-Eastex, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 11-12)
    - Time: Budget: 1976, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 13)
    - Time-Life Films: Budget and Two Year Plan: 1976, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 14)
    - Truman/Life, 1973 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 15)
    - Truman/Life [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R45)
    - Welch, Paul, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 16)
    - Women, 1973-1976 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 17)
    - Women's Issue, 1975 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 18)
    - Yale University: Recruiting Program, 1973 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 19)
  - Subseries I.C. Chief of Correspondents Richard Duncan Files, 1980-1987; 1.7 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
    Biographical / Historical
    Richard Duncan, better known as Dick Duncan, first shows up in Time Inc. department heads lists in October 1966 when he was serving as Caribbean bureau chief. It is unknown if he held other positions at Time Inc. prior to this. Duncan remained in this position until March 1969 when he was transferred to the Ottawa bureau to serve as their bureau chief. In 1972, Duncan disappeared from the department heads list but reappears in 1974 as the bureau chief of Beverly Hills. Sometime between 1974 and 1978, Duncan becomes deputy chief of correspondents and then chief of correspondents. Duncan remains in this position until May 1986.
    The Richard Duncan Files contain materials collected by or sent to Duncan from 1980 to 1987. While originally thought to be general chief of correspondent files, these materials were found within their own box and had a single creator. There were no other chief of correspondent files other than the ones created by Duncan. The type of materials in this subseries are similar to the materials found the General Files subseries within the Chief of Correspondent Files. Included in this subseries are lists of meeting attendees, biographical data sheets, dispatches, translations of court documents, dinner event menus, a report on background material for the Korean delegation dinner, CVs, travel itinerary, and correspondence. The correspondence featured in this subseries discusses fellowship programs, meetings, new hires, travel plans, stringers, invitations, consultant reports, proposed projects, schedules, and itinerary.
    - Africa and South America Trip: 1982, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 20)
    - Africa and South America Trip: 1982 [RESTRICTED], undated (Offsite-box R46)
    - Austrian Chancellor, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 21)
    - Austrian Foreign Minister: Sept. 27, 1984 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 22)
    - Avila, Joaquin: Lunch, 1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 23)
    - Ben-Elissar, Eli, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 24)
    - Beneat, Daniel, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 25)
    - Bentsen, Lloyd, 1984 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 26)
    - Bet, Shin, 1980 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 27)
    - Boat Ride, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 28)
    - Borge, Tomas, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 29)
    - Boston Plans, 1980 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 30)
    - Breakfasts/News Desks: New York Bureau, 1986 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 31)
    - Brown, Jerry, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 32)
    - Buckley, James, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 33)
    - Bureau Chiefs, 1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 34)
    - Carrington, Peter: Lunch, 1984 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 35)
    - Central America: Newstour, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 36-37)
    - Central America: Newstour [RESTRICTED], 1983 (Offsite-box R46)
    - Central America: Trip, undated (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 38)
    - Chicago: Council on Foreign Affairs: Ogden, Chris, 1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 39)
    - Christmas Party, 1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 40)
    - Coffee: Italian Minister of Defense: Spadolini, 1985 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 41)
    - Council on Foreign Relations [EMPTY], undated (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 42)
    - Curran, Ed, 1984 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 43)
    - De Michelis, Gianni, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 44)
    - Diaries, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 45)
    - Dole, Bob: Lunch, 1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 46)
    - East Germany Project, 1984 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 47)
    - Economic Business Seminar, 1984 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 48)
    - Elekdag, Sukru, 1982 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 49)
    - Europe Trip: 1983 January, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3186, Folder 50)